Okay, so today's דף daf is ל"ו Lamed Vav 36. And we
pick up at the very top of ל"ו עמוד א' Lamed Vav
Amud Aleph and we're dealing with the issue that when a widow
comes to collect from the estate instead of having her make a
שבועה shvuah because of the heavy consequences of a שבועת שקר shvuat
sheker even in an unintentional one, they switch to having her make
a נדר, neder, a vow. And now the גמרא, Gemara, and we
actually start an interesting issue where according to some אמוראים, Amoraim, they
were afraid that they couldn't trust that, and then they have the
they wouldn't let her even make a vow and then she couldn't
collect and it showed an undermining of the whole purpose of the
תיקון עולם, Tikkun Olam, you know, and of the and of the
understanding that there's a necessity to fix the situation. And then there
was sort of like a reverse, then there was a pushback on
that to get back to the original state. But I mention that
because we're going to be seeing some more of that coming up
as well about how some of these institutions of תיקון עולם Tikkun
Olam might have experienced some pushback at a later stage. Anyway, now
we're dealing with the issue that she makes a נדר neder and
the גמרא's Gemara question is, well, why will that נדר neder suffice?
First of all, can she make it once she's already married? Then
her husband can annul it. Can she make it in general and
then a חכם, chakham, she can go to a sage and have
it and have it voided? So the גמרא Gemara actually said when
she's already married, according to one opinion, she could not make it
because then her husband will just annul it and it won't prove
anything. According to another opinion, it would be possible to make it,
but if she made it ברבים, be-rabbim, if she made it in
public, and maybe that would exclude it from being voided. Now one
thing I should say about that because we're about to get to
the difference between ברבים be-rabbim and על דעת רבים al da'at rabbim
is that ברבים be-rabbim means in public, right? And whatever the definition
of public, רש"י Rashi says ten, and על דעת רבים al da'at
rabbim means it's sort of like it's not just based on what
I have in mind, but somehow it would be based on the
on what the ציבור tzibbur would have in mind, at least theoretically.
So we'll see in a moment about what that means, but here
תוספות Tosafot points out that when it comes to the issue of
the husband being able to void it, על דעת רבים al da'at
rabbim would not help. Even though על דעת רבים al da'at rabbim
in other situations might prevent any vow from being voided,
that's when because the nature of the process of going to a
sage to annul the vow, to void the vow, is that I
say, well, under these circumstances I wouldn't have made it. It wasn't
really my intent, it wasn't really my דעת, da'at, had I, you
know, I made it in error, I made it without due consideration
and so on. So if it's not about my דעת, da'at, if
it's somehow dependent on everybody else's דעת, da'at, so that closes off
the possibility of going to the sage. That's the idea of על
דעת רבים. al da'at rabbim. But it's somewhat of the opposite or
it could be the opposite when it comes to the husband. When
the husband voids his wife's vows, does a הפרה hafarah of his
wife's vow, it doesn't matter what she was thinking. She could have
been a hundred percent committed to it, no טעות ta'ut at all.
He just has the power to void it. So doing על דעת
רבים al da'at rabbim doesn't help. So what? You didn't have a
טעות. ta'ut. My why, you know, if my wife didn't have a
טעות, ta'ut, I don't care that the רבים rabbim didn't have a
טעות. ta'ut. I have the power to void it. Who cares what
דעת da'at is involved? Okay, but ברבים be-rabbim might work because ברבים
be-rabbim means it's no longer private affair between the two of us.
If it's a private affair between me and my wife, I can
void her vow. Once it's done in public and it's a matter
of like public record,
then it takes it out of the again that like private realm
and I can't void it. Okay, so that's so again, so what's
the issue about about how can
does the נדר neder work if she's married? According to one opinion,
no. According to another opinion, yes, if she makes it not על
דעת רבים al da'at rabbim that wouldn't help, but ברבים be-rabbim according
to this opinion, if a wife makes a vow in public, okay,
then that might exclude a husband's ability to void it and then
that would be a solution in this case. One minute, that's the
case about if she's married. In a normal case, how do we
close off the possibility that she might go to a sage and
get it get it permitted? And then the נדר neder won't do
its won't be able to be effective in בית beit to let
her collect? So here we have two or three answers. Number one
is maybe when you go to a sage you are צריך לפרט
את הנדר, tzarikh lefareit et haneder, you have to give the circumstances
under which it's made and therefore specifically for reasons such as this,
so the sage will know that I can't allow this vow, this
vow allows you to collect, right? It's not something that I could
allow. Okay, so that's one opinion. Another opinion says no, normally you
don't have to be מפרט הנדר, mifaret haneder, a phrase that once
you start giving information it won't be complete information, and according to
the other opinion that you are not מפרט את הנדר, mifaret et
haneder, so or you don't have to be, so we're afraid that
it will be, so how do you stop going to the sage?
So according to this opinion, it would only be, for example, if
the only way we would allow this to work is a vow
that would the vow would have to be made either again ברבים,
be-rabbim, in public, or על דעת רבים. al da'at rabbim. And that's
what we're about to explore now, this issue of a vow made
in public or a vow made on the דעת da'at of the
public, on the intent, on the will of the masses, and that
that may be the only case in which this vow is that
this woman makes, even an unmarried woman makes or a widowed woman
makes. it makes, if in order to allow her to collect from
her dead husband's estate. Michael, you had a question?
Yeah, I would have thought is that it would have been sort
of על דעת רבים al das rabim would have trumped it. I
thought ברבים berabbim just would have been like alright, you know, the
ten people there or whoever's there, you know, sort of listening, they're
witnesses, but על דעת רבים al das rabim is like not only
are we witnesses, but like we're really paying attention. You know what
I mean? Like it's, you know, with our knowledge and awareness and
cognizance.
Right, well that is the difference, but על דעת רבים al das
rabim doesn't need anybody to be present. It's just no, well, you
could always combine the two, but they are two different concepts. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay? So the גמרא
Gemara says,
so I understand. Okay. So let's see, three lines from the bottom
ל"ה עמוד ב'. Lamed Heh Amud Beis. So let's repeat that. ואמרת
דאינו צריך לפרט את הנדר, veamarta deino tzarich lofart es haneder,
but if you don't normally have to detail the conditions of how
the vow was made, ליחוש דלמא אזיל לגבי חכם ושרי ליה, leicheish
dilma azil legabi chacham vesheri lei,
let's be afraid that somebody will go to a sage and the
sage will permit it. Okay, so how, you know, so how will
this work that a woman can make, I think this is a
case of him. What's the case here? כהן? Kohen?
Oh,
כהן, Kohen, thank you, right. So the case we had just dealt
with was a כהן Kohen who makes a vow to not get
benefit from his wife that he's not allowed to be married to,
let's say a case of a גרושה. gerusha. How do we let
that vow work and let him do the עבודה? avodah? Maybe he'll
just go and release himself from the vow. So a similar case
to our case of the אלמנה. almanah. So the גמרא Gemara says,
top of ל"ו עמוד א', Lamed Vav Amud Aleph, דמדירין ליה ברבים.
demadirin lei berabbim.
So we make him take the vow in public and that will
close off the ability of doing a התרה hatara of going to
a חכם. chacham. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. הניחא למאן
דאמר נדר שהודר ברבים אין לו הפרה. Hani-cha leman d'amar neder shehudur
berabbim ein lo hafara. That's
if good according to the opinion that if it's in public it
cannot, you cannot be annulled by the husband and therefore presumably cannot
be allowed by cannot be voided by the חכם chacham either. אלא
למאן דאמר יש לו הפרה, Ella leman d'amar yesh lo hafara,
but according to the idea that it can be annulled by the
husband and similarly we're assuming by the sage, מאי איכא למימר? mai
ika l'meimar? So what solution do you have? So the גמרא Gemara
says, דמדירין ליה על דעת רבים. demadirin lei al das rabim. Ah,
so not that it's in public, but it's on the דעת das
of the public. On the interaction of public opinion.
Something, that's a way of saying it, yeah, like how the public
would what we presume the public would intend for such a right
and for such a case. It's really distinct category. Well, it takes
it out of my subjective דעת. das. Okay, what it's now but
it doesn't mean independent
of how what they're thinking.
Right, so let's take a look. Let's the גמרא Gemara will clarify
this. דאמר אמימר, Damar Ameimar, because אמימר Ameimar says הלכתא אפילו
למאן דאמר נדר שהודר ברבים יש לו הפרה, hilchasa afilu leman d'amar
neder shehudur berabbim yesh lo hafara,
there was done in public, it can still be voided, אבל על
דעת רבים אין לו הפרה. aval al das rabim ein lo hafara.
Now הפרה hafara here probably means התרה hatara because תוספות Tosafos already
pointed out, first of all, הפרה hafara that that would be the
standard case we're talking about and that is the case we're talking
about here, and תוספות Tosafos already pointed out that על דעת רבים
al das rabim wouldn't work by a case of a husband being
מיפר meifer because דעת das doesn't really matter in that case. So
we're probably here talking about התרה. hatara. Okay, so anyway, so even
if על דעת רבים al das rabim if ברבים berabbim doesn't work
to close off the ability of a חכם chacham voiding it, but
על דעת רבים al das rabim would. Okay, now the גמרא's Gemara
going to clarify in its next line some of the mechanics of
על דעת רבים. al das rabim. Wait, let me
what? You're saying the no, you're saying the opposite.
I was saying the opposite by הפרה, hafara, by the case of
the husband. That's why I'm trying to get to understand, okay, that
there is
if ברבים berabbim does work, it could be that it's more absolute,
right? Because ברבים berabbim could say once it's in public, it's a
matter of public sort of record. Doesn't matter that what anybody is
thinking, it's a matter of public record and it's no longer a
private affair and I can't get my husband to annul it, I
can't get the sage to void it, all of that is in
terms of it being a sort of a, you know, a personal
type of an issue as opposed to once it's become a sort
of a public, a public issue. That's so if it does work,
then it actually completely seals off the ability, the presumably there would
be no exceptions, it would it would prevent even my husband from
annulling it because it's not a question it's not a question of
דעת, das, right? So that would be if it does work. But
there are opinions that says that doesn't help. Just because you did
it in public doesn't change the nature of the vow. So this
is saying that even according to those opinions that doing it in
public doesn't change the nature of the vow, they would admit that
doing it על דעת רבים al das rabim is relevant. Because since
דעת das is always relevant to a vow, doing it על דעת
רבים al das rabim is relevant. So the difference is if ברבים
berabbim works, then in way then it's then it's sort of it's
it's broader and more absolute than על דעת רבים. al das rabim.
But there are opinions that it doesn't work. Who cares that you
said it in public? Since when does that change what the, you
know, the nature of the vow? על דעת רבים, al das rabim,
that will work. Okay, but if על דעת רבים al das rabim
works, it doesn't work in all cases. It might be it's it
might be that that על דעת רבים al das rabim ברבים berabbim
doesn't work at all and על דעת רבים al das rabim does
work. Okay, but nevertheless על דעת רבים al das rabim might not
work in a case of husband and wife because that their דעת
das doesn't matter. Okay, and where it also might not work is,
let's read. Let's read the next case, as the גמרא Gemara says
והני מילי לדבר רשות v'hani milei l'dvar reshus and anyway, that idea
that על דעת רבים al das rabbin prevents it from being annulled,
that's only when it's a matter of discretion. אבל לדבר מצוה, aval
l'dvar mitzvah, when the vow needs to be annulled to enable a
מצוה mitzvah to be done, it's getting in the way of a
מצוה, mitzvah, יש הפרה yesh hafarah it can be annulled. Okay? And
what's an example of this? כההוא מקרי דרדקי, k'hahu mikri dardeki, like
a case of this teacher of the elementary school teacher, teacher of
small children, דאסריה רב אחא על דעת רבים, d'asreih Rav Acha al
das rabbin, that רב אחא Rav Acha made him take a vow
on the דעת das of the רבים rabbin that he would like,
you know, that he could no longer teach the kids. And if
he were to teach, right, it was as we'll see, we'll get
to it. All right. That he could no longer teach and if
he would teach, maybe, you know, all of the fruit of the
world would be אסור assur to him or something of that nature.
And he made him take a vow, and he made him take
a vow in a way that it was על דעת רבים, al
das rabbin, so he could not reverse it, he couldn't go to
a חכם chacham and get it reversed. Okay? דהוה פשע בינוקי, d'hava
pasha b'yanukei, because he was negligent with the children, and that doesn't
mean that he didn't grade their papers, presumably it means that he
hit them. Okay. All right, everybody could we stop the comments. ואהדריה
רבינא, v'ahadrei Ravina, and then רבינא Ravina restored him to his post,
דלא אשתכח דדייק כוותיה, d'lo ishtakach d'dayek k'vosei, because they couldn't find
another teacher that was as good as him and as demanding of
the kids as he is. So obviously that's a very sad sort
of statement, I mean going back of course to a time in
what right a thousand years ago, fifteen hundred years
ago, when you know hitting kids I mean was in school was
a acceptable form of discipline, but it also is sad because it
makes you think of contemporary cases about sexual abuse where people will
gloss over
obvious signs of
about abusive and sexual abuse and so on because they'll say well
I mean he's such an effective educator and such a good teacher
and so on. So anyway,
but the point here is that it was understood to be that
this vow was getting in the way of the מצוה mitzvah of
educating the kids,
and therefore they released, he was able to be released from it.
Now what about the fact that it was על דעת רבים? al
das rabbin? But the argument is, oh okay, but the רבים rabbin
basically would say your personal subjective reasons that you wouldn't have taken
the vow in situation A, B, and C, that's not relevant to
us, the רבים, rabbin, we don't have those subjective reasons. Okay? So
that's not you cannot be released from your vow on the basis
of some type of טעות, to'us, an error, you know, if it
has to do with your subjective reality. That's the whole point of
making it a communal דעת. das. But to be released from it
based on an objective reality, had we known that it would have
gotten in the way of a מצוה, mitzvah, there's no way any
of us would have wanted a vow to get in the way
of a מצוה. mitzvah. So therefore that's considered a type of a
טעות. to'us. Again, the way התרה hatarah of a חכם chacham works
is that it identifies an error in your דעת. das. Okay? And
if it's על דעת רבים, al das rabbin, the subjective circumstances that
you might have not intended are no longer relevant, it doesn't make
it subjective, it makes it a communal דעת. das. We don't share
those subjective circumstances. But if it's a type of an error, thank
you so much, but if it's a type of an error
that we as a community, a circumstance we as a community never
would have, you know, would have acknowledged there should not be a
vow in those cases, then it is a basis for recognized error
to release it. So that's the mechanism of על דעת רבים. al
das rabbin. So that mechanism is not absolute to prevent releasing, it
allows it in cases where the רבים rabbin would have obviously never
wanted there to be a vow, and it might not work according
to תוספות, Tosafos, it shouldn't work in a case of husband and
wife, which isn't based on the wife's vow, the husband's ability to
annul and the wife's דעת das has nothing to do with the
wife's דעת. das. So על דעת רבים al das rabbin is, what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is, is works according to everybody, everybody
agrees it's a mechanism that works, but it doesn't have absolute scope.
It works only with the חכם, chacham, not to prevent the husband,
and even there doesn't work in case of מצוה mitzvah or other
types of situations. If ברבים be-rabbin does work, and it's debated if
ברבים be-rabbin works, but if ברבים be-rabbin does work, it's a different
type of a mechanism. It makes it a public matter and not
a private matter and therefore takes it out of the realm of
the ability to be annulled, works whether it's for חכם, chacham, whether
for a husband and wife, and would have no exceptions. Okay? So
that's a very interesting difference between those two types of mechanisms.
So you're saying is there is an opinion out there that would
say the husband and wife he can't annul a) if it was
ברבים be-rabbin and b) if it was על דעת רבים, al das
rabbin, both cases.
No, there's no I mean at least I don't know if other
ראשונים Rishonim say. I know that תוספות Tosafos says that a husband
should never על דעת רבים al das rabbin will never stand in
the way of a husband and wife.
ברבים be-rabbin would? Yes. Okay.
Because exactly for that reason. דעת das is not relevant for husband.
No, well according to the opinions that ברבים be-rabbin works, that would
solve the case of husband, that would get in the way of
husband and wife.
Right, no, my question was like how do we פסקן? pasken? Or
do you have like both? In other words, someone would say no
matter what, I don't care about רבים, rabbin, I don't care about
על דעת רבים, al das rabbin, like.
Oh, is there an opinion that says neither works? Yes, or I
think תוספות Tosafos raises that, I forget if there's actually how he
concludes with that, yes.
I'm just a little confused on על דעת רבים al das rabbin
because. The husband has kind of control or
veto power over the דעת da'as of the wife, right? If it's
not her דעת da'as that made the vow, how does he have
veto power over the דעת da'as of the wife?
Because he doesn't—the mechanism doesn't work with—I mean, I guess you're right
if the logic of הפרה hafarah is "my will is stronger than
your will," you know, then when it's somebody else's will, it's not
that case. But it's not an issue of will, it's an issue
of, like, you know, it's just like, "I can't tolerate this vow
to be in our marriage," and you know, and because so, then
it's like—it's not about the will that was behind the vow. So
that's basically the point, that the case of annulling the wife's vow
is not because of her intent or her will, it's just the
husband's fundamental ability to, you know, say this vow can't be—sort of
stand—like, it's a power issue, but not a power of will, not
like a contest of wills. Right. But like, the phenomenon of this
vow, I can say is, you know, not acceptable to me. Yes.
This is if I last misunderstood—this would be—this was רבנו תם Rabbeinu
Tam's as well, he seems to be saying על דעת רבים al
das rabbim is like סתם. stam. Like, it's if one person can
actually know what the רבים. rabbim.
Yeah, that's a funny רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Yeah, I mean, yes,
that is an interesting רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. If you look in
the middle of that תוספות, Tosafot, he says, ועוד אומר רבנו תם
דעל דעת היינו כשאומר על דעת פלוני ופלוני אפילו שלא בפניהם דעל
דעת רבים צריך שידעו על מי הוא נדר ועל דעת רבים סתם
לאו כלום הוא.
Ve-od
omer
Rabbeinu Tam de-al das haynu k'shomer al das ploni u-ploni afilu she-lo
bifneihem d'al das rabbim tzarich she-yedu al mi hu nadar ve-al das
rabbim stam lav klum hu. Right.
You know what, like communal...
Yeah, but it's a very strange רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam because the
whole point of making it generic is to actually prevent—close off any
avenue. There's no—no particular person's subjective דעת da'as is relevant, it's just
the community as a whole. Well, the community as a whole takes
it out of any subjective circumstances, would limit it to cases where
there are objective circumstances that every—you know, everybody would agree should not
stand in the way of a vow. Yes.
All categories have to do with נדר, neder, right? Right. So, but
if they would have just kept with a שבועה... shvuah...
Right. So let's repeat that and then we'll go on, which is
a—now, you could be released from a שבועה shvuah if it's a
future-oriented שבועה shvuah in a similar way. I take a שבועה shvuah
that I will do X, that I won't do X. But if
it's a past-oriented שבועה, shvuah, taking a שבועה shvuah that I never
took any money from the estate, right, so then that's determined, then
that's not something that exists now as a thing that binds me
that I can be released from. At the moment those words go
out of my mouth, I'm either telling the truth or I'm lying.
And if I'm lying at that moment, then I made a שבועת
שקר. shvuas sheker. And there's nothing the חכם chacham can do later
that affects that. Right. So all of these issues about, wait a
minute, with a נדר neder you can be released from it is
only because we shifted from שבועה shvuah to נדר. neder. Absolutely. Okay,
so now let's continue. So תקנה takanah number two is, or in
the משנה, Mishnah, the next thing we saw was תיקון עולם. tikkun
olam. והעדים חותמין על הגט מפני תיקון עולם. Ve-ha-eidim chosmin al ha-get
mipnei tikkun olam. And the witnesses sign on a גט get for
the sake of תיקון עולם. tikkun olam. So, first of all, תוספות
Tosafot has a little discussion of whether you have the "vav"—והעדים חותמין
על הגט ve-ha-eidim chosmin al ha-get because the משנה Mishnah by the
אלמנה almanah says התקין רבן גמליאל הזקן שתהא נודרת כל מה שירצו.
Hitkin Rabban Gamliel ha-Zaken she-tehei noderes kol mah she-yirtzu. And then it
says והעדים חותמין, ve-ha-eidim chosmin, it sounds like that's part of רבן
גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel's תקנה. takanah. But actually תוספות Tosafot says it's going
to be clear from what we're going to read that this idea
of signing a גט get predated רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. Okay, so
he takes out the "vav". מפני תיקון עולם. Mipnei tikkun olam. Wait
a minute, you only sign a גט get because it's a, sort
of, you know, makes for the better running of the world, that
she has now a signed document and doesn't have to go looking
for the עדים eidim that were actually present? דאורייתא היא. De-oraisa hi.
It's biblical! דכתיב וכתוב בספר וחתום, De-chsiv ve-chasov be-sefer ve-chasom, "write in
a book" and a scroll and sign. ואמר רבא. Va-amar Rava. So,
so okay, so therefore and presumably that means that anything that's to
be defined as a legal document in the תורה, Torah, even if
it's not as—even if its purpose is not to serve to prove
as evidence that something took place, but as an instrument to use
it as a document of an instrument of divorce, it's only if
it actually has signed witnesses in the document itself. So why is
this a תיקון עולם? tikkun olam? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, let's
take a look. לא צריכא אלא לרבי אלעזר. Lo tzericha ela le-Rabbi
Elazar. It's needed for the position of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, דאמר
עדי מסירה כרתי, de-amar edei mesirah karsi, that he says that biblically
speaking, that this verse is actually not required for the definition of
a שטר shtar as another גמרא Gemara says, that's only עצה טובה
קא משמע לן, eitzah tovah ka mashma lan, just good advice. Okay?
And so we of חז"ל Chazal took the good advice of the
verse. But דאורייתא de-oraisa it's not needed. You could have something that
operates as a שטר, shtar, certainly as a שטר shtar that's a
what we call a שטר קנין, shtar kinyan, an instrument—a שטר shtar
that serves as an instrument to transfer field, to marry a woman,
to divorce a woman, to free a slave. When it's actually serving
as an instrument, it does not need the testimony as written—you know,
written into the שטר. shtar. Okay, it's just the good advice of
that verse, and we took that good advice. Okay, but דאורייתא, de-oraisa,
עדי מסירה כרתי, edei mesirah karsi, biblically speaking, the witnesses who are
physically present and observe it being handed over, those are the witnesses
that make it into a גט get and make it into a
valid document, or they're the witnesses that are necessary for the acta,
you know, because it's a דבר שבערוה, davar she-be-ervah, matter of personal
status requires witnesses, so they might be required. For just a transaction,
and it might also be considered that those physical witnesses who are
present is considered that their viewing of the giving over the גט
Get somehow becomes part of the, you know, validates the שטר shtar
itself. It's seen as part of the שטר, shtar, but they don't
have to write their names in it. They just have to be
physically present. That's all you need. Okay? Or not all, that's what
you need according to the תורה. Torah. So therefore that's biblically speaking.
But תקנו רבנן עדי חתימה, takinu rabanan eidei chasima, but the Rabbis
established that they should actually sign their names מפני תיקון העולם, mipnei
tikkun ha-olam, for the sake of the, you know, of the improvement
of the world. Why? דזימנין דמייתי סהדי, de-zimnin de-maisi sahadei, sometimes the
witnesses will die. אינמי, Inami, or דזימנין דאזלי למדינת הים, zimnin de-azli
li-medinas ha-yam, they'll go far away and there's our מדינת הים medinas
ha-yam again, and then this woman won't be able to prove that
she's divorced. So it serves as an instrument, but you know what
it doesn't serve as? It doesn't serve as evidence. So if the
woman is going to want a document that's going to be evidence
of her divorce, they have them go ahead and write their names
in. Now of course it's interesting because there could be alternatives before
she's divorced. Well, besides that, well, that's always true. But no, but
it could be that we would say that the document itself wouldn't
have the witnesses, but then after she was divorced, the בית דין
beis din would write up a, you know, a document that, you
know, a שטר shtar that would testify to the fact that it
happened. But you know, that just requires yet another document to be
written. And you know, this way the woman the same document the
woman gets that divorces her that necessarily she must receive will be
the document that serves as, you know, something she puts in the
safety deposit box and will serve as her evidence. Just to remind
you there is a whole debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about what
happens if once they did sign the document, if the עדים, eidem,
once their document is signed, to what degree do they really become
דאורייתא d'oraisa part of the שטר? shtar? And the most obvious נפקא
מינה nafka mina of that is, let's say there were not עדי
מסירה eidei mesirah present. Let's say according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
it was given only with the signed signatures and with no עדי
מסירה. eidei mesirah. So according to a number of ראשונים Rishonim that
actually could work as well. That רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer admits that
this is a that this actually if they sign then even though
it's not required דאורייתא, d'oraisa, it does דאורייתא d'oraisa become part of
the שטר, shtar, and then it becomes as if the signed signatures
when handed over become like the physical witnesses that are present to
testify and to, you know, be there to observe the giving over
of the שטר. shtar. So according to some ראשונים Rishonim this works
so much not only as evidence, but it even not only works
again not that the Rabbis created this, the Rabbis required it be
signed, but the argument would be that according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer once signed, that becomes a תורה Torah recognized valid testimony that
exists within the document, not just to prove that she's divorced but
actually to serve as a substitute, as a substitute for the need
for the physical witnesses to be present. So there's an interesting so
there's an interesting whole debate of ראשונים Rishonim about how that functions.
Another נפקא מינה nafka mina would be as we saw way at
the beginning of the מסכת, maseches, what if according to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer the witnesses signed it שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. שלא לשמה,
Shelo lishma, right? So once you're saying that the signing is gets
incorporated into the nature and identity of the שטר, shtar, it wasn't
necessary, but if you did it, it became part of the שטר,
shtar, then how much does all the requirements of the שטר shtar
apply to the signing of the witnesses as well? Yes. I didn't
understand. So the בעל's ba'al going to come in and מערער ma'er
and says oh you know this is a golem like whatever. עדי
מסירה Eidei mesirah say no no I was there when he gave
it. It's one against two. So once according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer the עדים eidem signed, then if he's מערער ma'er he's not
believed because it's also two against one? Well, no, I mean it's
the same הלכה halacha as what do you call it, as רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir once the witness signatures are validated. Before they're validated.
Before they're validated according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you have to
get them validated unless it was חיתום chosam and בפני נחתם. bifanai
nechtam. It's all the same mechanism. And if it was validated he
wouldn't be believed. Exactly. Yes. So רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer saying the
witnesses, the signing witnesses are not really necessary. Right. But once they're
there they can replace the witnesses who saw the actual. That is
according to some ראשונים Rishonim they say that, right, that's debated. And
how does this relate to a כתובה kesubah or דת יהודית? das
yehudis? In other words in terms of that you need signatures on.
No, so a כתובה kesubah is a document that is not an
instrument. It's a document that only testifies to the assumption of debt
of responsibility. So you only need signing witnesses. Exactly, exactly. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. רב יוסף אמר אפילו
תימא רבי מאיר. Rav Yosef amar afilu teima Rabbi Meir. Even according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, yes it's true that you needed witnesses,
but when it says that they anyway signed, but what it means
that they made a תיקון עולם tikkun olam was how they would
sign. Okay. התקין שיהו עדים מפרשים שמותיהם בגיטין. Hiskin she-yehu eidem mefarshim
shemoseihem be-gittin. They would spell out their names. They would write a
fully identifying signature. מפני תיקון העולם. Mipnei tikkun ha-olam. דתניא, De-tanya, because
we taught in a בריתא, Baraisa, בראשונה היה כותב אני פלוני חתמתי
עד. barishonah hayah kosev ani ploni chasamti eid. Originally you would not
write your name, you would just write I, you know, I, it
just says פלוני. ploni. It just says פלוני. ploni. What? One minute.
ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon מעיקרא mei-ikara לא יחוש lo yeichosh
ממן meman אלא ela אני פלוני חתמתי עד ani ploni chasamti eid
ולא ינוקב שם אמצי. velo yenokeiv shem amtsayei. No, no, you're right,
I missed whatever, fine. Okay, right. So originally you would just write
your first name. You know, I, ראובן, Reuven, have signed as a
witness. Okay. אם כתב ידו יוצא ממקום אחר כשר. im kesav yado
yotzei mimakom acher kosher. Now if your handwriting we knew from another
place, then it would be כשר, kosher, that would be fine. We
would know look, there's somebody, you know, we know this is ראובן
Reuven Schwartz's handwriting and he wrote it from another place, so we'd
know that it's a legitimate signature. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, but if
not, פסול. pasul. And the problem would be if you said wait,
wait, we don't recognize this signature and we don't know who this
guy is. It's a ראובן, Reuven, there are a million ראובן. Reuvens.
How are we going to find out if this is the legitimate
signature of this person if we don't know who the person is?
Right, so we would be totally stuck. אמר רבן גמליאל תקנה גדולה
התקינו. Amar Rabban Gamliel takana gedola hiskinu. They made a big תקנה,
takana, so notice here the use of the word תקנה takana in
this ברייתא braisa indicates that this might have been the תקנה takana
we were talking about. Okay. שיהיו מפרשים שמותיהם בגיטין מפני תיקון עולם.
she'yehu mefarshim shemoseihem begittin mipnei tikkun olam. They would say aloud explicitly,
they would ראובן בן יעקב, Reuven ben Yaakov, right? So okay, so
they would be much more specific and then they would be able
to find, you know, does anybody know a ראובן בן יעקב Reuven
ben Yaakov and they'd be able to find the guy, does anybody
have any signatures from a ראובן בן יעקב Reuven ben Yaakov and
if we know whose signature we're talking about we would be able
to מקיים mekayem them. Narrow it down to a thousand guys. Well,
okay exactly. Same city also? Okay, no, not in the signature. ובסימנא
לא. u'vesimana lo. Now if there's two... the גמרא Gemara says if
there's two people in the same town that have the same name
and the same father's name then you would make it three generations.
Okay, so when there are people with duplicate signatures, you know, you
would want... okay, so now the גמרא Gemara actually that's more about
the, excuse me, that's more about the person about the right about
the name in the גט, get, about the husband and the wife,
I'm sorry, not about the witnesses. What's the difference? ובסימנא. u'vesimana. Because
we... it's a patriarchy. ובסימנא לא. u'vesimana lo. Now are we saying
that you have to actually the only way to do it is
by using your name and your father's name and so on and
not by doing some type of a symbol? So והא רב צייר
כוורא, ve'ha Rav tziyer kavra, but רב Rav drew a little fish.
רב חנינא צייר חרותא, Rav Chanina tziyer charusa, and רב חנינא Rav
Chanina drew a palm tree. Apparently instead of his signature he drew
a picture of a fish. And רב חנינא Rav Chanina drew a
palm tree. That's right. רב חסדא סמך, Rav Chisda Samech, רב חסדא
Rav Chisda just drew a letter סמך Samech for חסדא. Chisda. רב
הושעיה עין, Rav Oshaya Ayin, I guess aya for הושעיה, Oshaya, okay.
רבה בר רב הונא צייר מקותא, Rabba bar Rav Huna tziyer makusa,
and he drew a... what's this מקותא... makusa... oh, a sail, a
sail of a ship. Okay, so anyway, so you see you can
just draw little symbols and that counts. So which is so funny
also because because there's two questions. Number one is how do we
know who signed it to be מקיים mekayem it and number two
is that we could think that it would be the drawing would
be distinctive enough as handwriting is in a signature that you could
actually be מקיים mekayem it. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara says, but
that doesn't bother the גמרא, Gemara, it presumes that. But then it
gets back to the problem of how is this better than like,
you know, than first names? How do you know, hey did anybody
know anybody who has a fish? Right? Like I mean how do
you go out and find out if you don't know who signed
it, right, how are you מקיים mekayem it? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, שאני רבנן דבקיאי בסימנייהו. shani rabbanan de'bekiei besimanaihu. No, no,
the רבנן rabbanan apparently this was a thing among the rabbinic class,
you know that they would have these little pictures, they would have
these little symbols and people knew and knew them by their symbols.
Oh, that's a רב חסדא Rav Chisda symbol, you know, so therefore
it wasn't a problem to be מקיים mekayem because they were known
by their symbols. So the גמרא Gemara says and again presumably it
would be distinctive enough that you couldn't forge it. So the גמרא
Gemara says מעיקרא במאי אפתינו. me'ikara be'mai apteinu. That's all very nice
once they get to be known by their symbols, but it's a
little circular. How did they start using their symbols, right? If you're
not allowed to use something that you can't be identified by, how
did you use your symbol signing a שטר shtar if at the
beginning when you weren't yet identified by it? Right? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, בדסקי, be'diskei, in like personal correspondence. So they if
they start having a lot of personal correspondence and you sign your
name with a symbol and everybody starts to know it then you
can start using that symbol on your שטר. shtar. Okay, again assuming
that it's distinctive enough and that it you know so it can't
be forged. You have to make a public declaration: Since the learning
is so sharp, that hatchet on the board should be your symbol.
I don't know about that. Okay anyway yeah. Yes. All right. Now
let's take a look. Now we move on to פרוזבול. Pruzbul. Okay?
Okay so הלל התקין פרוזבול. Hillel hiskin Pruzbul. הלל Hillel established פרוזבול.
Pruzbul. Now we'll discuss in a minute what פרוזבול Pruzbul where the
etymology of that word might mean. Anyway תנן התם, tenan hasam, exactly.
תנן התם. tenan hasam. We taught over there. I don't know about
that. Okay, anyway, yeah. Yes. Okay now, let's take a look. Now
we move on to dum-ta-da-dum פרוזבול. Prozbol. Okay. Okay, so הלל Hillel
התקין hitskin פרוזבול. Prozbol. הלל Hillel established פרוזבול. Prozbol. Now we'll discuss
in a minute what פרוזבול, Prozbol, where, what the etymology of that
word might mean. Anyway, תנן התם, tnat hasom, exactly. תנן התם. tnat
hasom. We taught over there in שביעית. Shvi'is. Okay. פרוזבול אינו משמט.
Prozbol einu meshamet. If something is written through a פרוזבול, Prozbol, it
doesn't get, it doesn't get annulled on שמיטה. Shmita. You do not
get released from the debt on שמיטה. Shmita. וזו מן הדברים, Vezo
min hadvarim, this is off from the משנה Mishna over there in
שביעית. Shvi'is. This is one of the things שהתקין הלל הזקן She'hitkin
Hillel Hazaken that הלל הזקן Hillel Hazaken established. שראה העם שנמנעו מלהלוות
זה לזה. She'ra'ah ha'am she'nimnu milhalvos zeh lazeh. He saw that people
were no longer lending money to one another when the שמיטה Shmita
year was coming near. Okay. ועברו מה שכתוב בתורה. Ve'avru ma shekatuv
batorah. They transgressed what's written in the תורה. Torah. השמר לך פן
יהיה דבר עם לבבך בליעל. Hishamer lecha pen yihyeh davar im levavecha
bliya'al. Watch yourself, guard yourself lest you have this thought, this treacherous
thought, saying that the שמיטה Shmita is coming and you won't lend
to the poor person. עמד והתקין פרוזבול. Amad vehitkin Prozbol. So he
created פרוזבול Prozbol to allow people to that they would lend to
the poor and that שמיטה Shmita would no longer annul the debts.
Now I need to say something very important here about how this
is framed. Because for a lot of people they go, oh yes,
you know, look at that, you know, the rabbis getting around what
the תורה Torah is trying to do. The תורה Torah wants to
annul it, the rabbis don't like it, so they find this workaround.
So the interesting thing is that the way it is framed is
not that way. The way it is framed is not this הלכה
Halacha of שמיטה Shmita is creating too much of a burden on
the creditors and we can't survive within it in our economy. It
wasn't explained that way. It was explained in terms of מצוות, Mitzvot,
that the current situation is causing the transgression of biblical מצוות. Mitzvot.
People are transgressing not lending to the poor. So the best way
to satisfy the תורה's, Torah's, not just our economic societal needs, but
the best way to satisfy the תורה's Torah's concern that these מצוות
Mitzvot are observed is by creating this reality of a פרוזבול. Prozbol.
So now that's not to say that there aren't times when sometimes
the human needs has to lead to certain types of תקנות Takanot
and certain types of workaround. Okay, but it's always better if it
can be framed in terms of that this is actually compromising a
מצווה Mitzvah of the תורה Torah itself, the current situation. So if
we prevent the debts from being annulled, now even in that case
you have to choose which of the מצוות Mitzvot is going to
trump. Is it better to people to transgress not lending but at
least we're fulfilling the מצווה Mitzvah of annulling the debt? Or is
it better to have the people not transgress the מצווה Mitzvah of
not lending, have them lend, and then but we won't be fulfilling
annulling the debts, right? It's still a tradeoff even in terms of
the math of the biblical math, the מצווה Mitzvah equation. So there's
no question that הלל Hillel would rather from a social perspective, you
know, and the well-being of the poor, of those two, rather that
people lend money and the debts don't get annulled, than people don't
lend money and whatever debts do exist do get annulled, right? You
understand that there's still going to be a choice, but it starts
by framing it as a competition of two תורה Torah mandates that
the תורה Torah recognizes the challenge. The תורה Torah says, lend money
but the debts still be annulled, but don't let that stop you
from lending money. The תורה Torah recognizes that people are going to
be tempted not to lend money and that's going to be a
challenge. So if one of those has to give, which one is
going to have to give? Now it's quite likely that somebody with
less of a vision than הלל Hillel would say, look, we have
a whole biblical institution of annulling debt, it's part of the שמיטה
Shmita year, just because individuals are transgressing, we can't undermine this whole
major part of what the שמיטה Shmita year is about, right? So
fine, individuals will transgress and I'm going to say that the basic
point of departure is that the debts have to be annulled. And
that's what you're going to find. הלל Hillel says no, you know,
the more important thing for even for the poor, it's not more
important that for the poor's own well-being it's more important that they
get the money and have to pay it back than that the
debts be annulled and they don't get the money to begin with.
Okay, so again, so the point here is that הלל Hillel did
not start by saying this מצווה Mitzvah won't work nowadays, we have
to find a workaround. He said he said people are transgressing and
a biblical violations are being done and therefore we can either allow
that situation to continue or we can change the annulling of the
debt so that these violations won't be done. So he makes it
a tradeoff between two מצוות Mitzvot as it were. And he obviously
sides in favor of the choice that is what he feels is
going to be in the best interest of the poor, yes. Does
anybody discuss it in the context of this is a reduction of
faith in השם, Hashem, the whole idea of you know that השם
Hashem will take care of you if you fulfill the מצווה? Mitzvah?
Right. I mean that's I think I don't know if it's framed
that way but that's presumably correct. I mean now by the way,
the תורה Torah doesn't say that about annulling the debts. The תורה
Torah says that about not working the field, that God will ensure
that there will be whatever, you know, but it does not say
that but it doesn't say that like you know if you annul
the debts God will pay you back for the money you lent.
But we're told that by שבת, Shabbos, if you spend money on
ערב שבת... Erev Shabbos... God will pay you back. But anyway, but
yeah, but it's not framed that way. Now I do want to
say of course that the exact same issue came up in שמיטה
shemitah observance, not the annulling of debt, but שמיטה shemitah observance in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So you look around and say that and
it just got renewed because of course the recent רבנות rabbanut is
so פרום frum that they can't rely on רב קוק's Rav Kook
היתר מכירה heter mechirah and how do you look at the situation?
Do you say that thousands of people, millions of people are going
to violate and therefore we have to find a technical workaround and
sell all of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to a non-Jew, which that
really seems like much more of a fiction than הלל's Hillel פרוזבול,
pruzbul, but okay, or do you say no, since when do we
compromise on the fact that people aren't observing the מצוות? mitzvos? We're
just going to keep everything natural the way it is and let
people that violate it let them violate, right? So it's the same
type of a trade-off. Okay, but it's not that רב קוק Rav
Kook just starts by saying oh economic, I mean maybe he did
say it at some level, he also did say that economically in
ישוב ארץ ישראל yishuv Eretz Yisrael whatever this isn't viable, but in
addition it could also be framed as an issue not just about
whether it's economically viable, but whether it is it's a competition of
two מצוות mitzvos as it were, not just sort of the human
dimension which is an important dimension in פסק psak but people don't
always give it the necessary weight. So it could be framed just
as a מצוה mitzvah dimension. Is it more important the whole country
keep the מצוה mitzvah of שמיטה shemitah and half of the country
violate it, or is it more important that we find a workaround
to the מצוה mitzvah of שמיטה, shemitah, right? A very similar type
of a question. Okay, so anyway let's take a look back at
the גמרא. Gemara. זהו גופו של פרוזבול, zehu gufo shel pruzbul, this
is the essence, the actual script of text of the פרוזבול. pruzbul.
מוסרני לכם פלוני ופלוני דיינים שבמקום פלוני, mosrani lachem ploni u-ploni dayanim
she-bimkom ploni, I am handing over to you ראובן Reuven and שמעון,
Shimon, the judges in such and such a place, so you identify
the בית דין, beis din, שכל חוב שיש לי אצל פלוני, she-kol
chov she-yesh li etzel ploni, that in any debt that I have
by a certain person, any money that this person owes me, שאגבנו
כל זמן שארצה, she-agvenu kol zman she-ertzeh, that I am retaining the
right to collect it whenever I want. והדיינים חותמים למטה או העדים,
ve-ha-dayanim chosmim lemata o ha-edim, and the judges sign below or the
witnesses. So this is, so that doesn't really explain the mechanism. This
just says I'm making a declaration that I'm going to plan to
collect it regardless. Okay, very nice, you're going to plan to collect
it regardless. Okay, what's the mechanism by which that works? So in
the משנה mishnah over there and elsewhere the גמרא Gemara identifies this
with the principle of what's called מוסר שטרותיו לבית דין, moseir shtrotav
le-veis din, that even though you say I plan on collecting it,
since you are informing the בית דין, beis din, it's sort of
like you give the authority to collect the debt over to the
בית דין. beis din. And therefore it's not, the תורה Torah says
when the שמיטה shemitah comes you shall not exact it from your
neighbor. Okay, but it's no longer me who's in a position of
power vis-a-vis my neighbor to be demanding and exacting the debt. I've
handed it over to that responsibility over to the בית דין. beis
din. So since there's no particular individual, it's sort of the communal
בית דין beis din that has the right to collect the debt
now, then the debt doesn't get annulled. Okay, that's the mechanism. For
example, so if you look at רש"י Rashi he says מוסרני לכם,
mosrani lachem, so רש"י Rashi says about I don't know twenty lines
from the bottom, twenty-five lines, אשטרותיי שתהיו אתם נוגשים, ashterotai she-tihyu atem
nogshim, you will be the ones to demand it and exact it,
ואני לא אגוש, ve-ani lo egosh, I will not. So it's funny,
the language is I'll collect it whenever I want but basically the
logic is maybe I'll collect it from you guys, anyway, but you're
the ones now who have the responsibility for it. וכן מוקי דיש
כח ביד חכמים להפקיר ממונו של זה וליתן לזה. ve-chan muki de-yesh
koach be-yad chachamim le-hafkir mamono shel zeh ve-litein le-zeh. Okay, so רש"י
Rashi doesn't here spell that out, but the idea is about מוסר
שטרותיו לבית דין, moseir shtrotav le-veis din, it's no longer my personal
debt or owed to me, you're taking it over so it's somehow
out of that category. Okay, but that doesn't really work on a
דאורייתא d'Oraisa level, if that worked on a דאורייתא d'Oraisa level you
wouldn't need הלל's Hillel תקנה. takanah. It is a little questionable because
some say well one minute, if that is a way of getting
around it why was הלל's Hillel תקנה? takanah? And some say well
it's generally understood to be that it's sort of like that's the
דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, that's the sort of claim of how it doesn't look
like a direct violation of the תורה Torah because it's framed as
it's no longer your debt, it's the בית דין's beis din debt.
But that's still a fiction. Okay, it's not really the בית דין's
beis din debt, it really is yours. So really you did need
הלל's Hillel תקנה takanah to come along and make this work. But
then the question becomes or how did תקנה takanah make it work?
If it is a fiction and the תורה Torah says the debt
should be annulled, how does this work? So that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי
איכא מידי, u-mi ika midi, and the גמרא Gemara says ומי איכא
מידי דמדאורייתא משמטה שביעית, u-mi ika midi de-mi-d'Oraisa meshamta shevi'is, is there
anything that at a דאורייתא d'Oraisa level the שביעית shevi'is should annul,
והתקין הלל דלא משמטה, ve-hiskin Hillel de-lo meshamta, and הלל Hillel established
that it should not be משמט? meshamet? How could such a thing
happen? How could he go ahead and undermine a דאורייתא d'Oraisa if
the תורה Torah really does annul the debt? So אמר אביי בשביעית
בזמן הזה ורבי היא, amar Abaye bi-shevi'is ba-zman ha-zeh ve-Rebbi hi, it's
talking about שמיטה shemitah nowadays and רבי Rebbi it's, שמיטה shemitah nowadays
the annulling of debt is only rabbinic, and since it's only rabbinic
the rabbis can take call an end to the annulling of debt
because the whole debts are anyway nowadays only rabbinic. Well, they first
made a תקנה takkana to continue the practices of שמיטה, Shmita, including
the annulling of debts. Okay, and then they found a way to
get a workaround around, around the. So why did they do it
from the outset? See what I mean is when he says that
it's only Rabbinic nowadays, isn't that a circular? The question was well
how do the rabbis, how can the rabbis negate? Well, no, so
then they're going to have to say, how do we know what
makes שמיטה Shmita Rabbinic nowadays? So that's going to be the next
line. So let's take a look. דתניא, Detanya, we learn in a
ברייתא. Braita. רבי אומר: Rebbi Omer: וזה דבר השמיטה שמוט. V'zeh dvar
hashmitah shamot. This is the manner of the שמיטה Shmita you should
release, okay, all your debts. בשתי שמיטות הכתוב מדבר. Bishtei shmitot hakatuv
midaber. It's talking about two שמיטות. shmitot. אחת שמיטת קרקע ואחת שמיטת
כספים. Achat shmitat karka v'achat shmitat kesafim. The שמיטה shmita of land
and the שמיטה shmita of moneys. בזמן שאתה משמט קרקע אתה משמט
כספים, בזמן שאי אתה משמט קרקע אי אתה משמט כספים. Bizman she'ata
m'shamet karka ata m'shamet kesafim, bizman she'ee ata m'shamet karka ee ata
m'shamet kesafim. When you, when you release the land, when you don't
work the land, there's שמיטה shmita of land, there's שמיטה shmita of
money. When there's not שמיטה shmita of the land, there's not שמיטה
shmita of the money. And the implication being nowadays there's not שמיטה
shmita of the land, so therefore there's no שמיטה shmita of the
money. Now why is there not שמיטה shmita of the land nowadays?
So you could say well after חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayit, the land
doesn't have let's say the קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushat Eretz Yisrael for
laws that are agricultural מצוות, mitzvot, and therefore there's no longer a
שמיטה, shmita, a biblical שמיטה. shmita. So there's also no longer biblical
releasing of debts. But we Rabbinically didn't want שמיטה shmita to end,
so we would have said that Rabbinically, as we do say, שמיטה
shmita still applies nowadays, okay? And then even though שמיטה shmita still
applies nowadays, and that would be whether the land and whether the
money, הלל Hillel came and said, you know what, for the money
thing we're not going to say it doesn't work at all, but
we're going to allow for a workaround. If you didn't do a
פרוזבול, Pruzbul, it'll still annul the money, but okay, but we're going
to allow for a workaround. So that's basically the גמרא's Gemara answer
that it's all Rabbinic, and therefore that allowed שמואל, Shmuel, actually not
שמואל, Shmuel, that allowed הלל Hillel to make a workaround. Now the
problem with this answer as רש"י Rashi points out is that why
is שמיטה shmita not נוהג noheg nowadays דאורייתא? d'Oraita? Presumably like I
said because it's post-חורבן. Churban. There's only a bit of a problem
which is the dating, because הלל Hillel lived pre-חורבן. Churban. So it's,
we're back to the question of how did הלל Hillel get around
it because in הלל's Hillel day it was still biblical. So רש"י
Rashi quotes another גמרא ירושלמי Gemara Yerushalmi or whatever that says, no
there's a different reason why it did, was not biblical even in
the time, שמיטה shmita was not biblical even in the time of
בית שני. Bayit Sheni. What's the reason? רש"י Rashi says that this
would be because שמיטה shmita would be the same way the שמיטה
shmita of money is dependent on the שמיטה shmita of land, the
שמיטה shmita of land is dependent on the practice of יובל. Yovel.
And יובל Yovel did not apply during בית שני Bayit Sheni because
יובל Yovel requires כל יושביה עליה, kol yoshveha aleha, all of the,
you know, inhabitants of the land, all the twelve tribes on the
land. And therefore even during בית שני Bayit Sheni there was no
יובל, Yovel, there was a Rabbinic יובל Yovel but not a דאורייתא
d'Oraita יובל, Yovel, and there was no דאורייתא d'Oraita שמיטה, shmita, there
was no שמיטת כספים, shmitat kesafim, so it was all Rabbinic, so
הלל Hillel made his תקנה. takkana. Okay, so that's what רש"י Rashi
says. רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam actually disagrees with that and has a
different reading of the גמרא, Gemara, but I am not going to
worry about that. Okay, that's the basic argument that it was all
Rabbinic, nowadays it's Rabbinic because of after the חורבן, Churban, and it
was even Rabbinic in the time of הלל Hillel because of, because
there was no יובל, Yovel, certainly it's Rabbinic nowadays, and that's why
the פרוזבול Pruzbul works. So the גמרא Gemara is still not happy,
because how did you make the original תקנה takkana to say that
there would be a Rabbinic annulling of debts? That also is a
question. ותקינו רבנן דתשמט זכר לשביעית. V'takinu rabanan d'tishmet zecher l'shviit. And
the rabbis started, I'm sorry I didn't get to the question yet.
The rabbis started with a תקנה takkana that you, like that we're
going to continue שמיטה shmita even nowadays, and even with no יובל,
Yovel, and even after the חורבן Churban we're going to continue שמיטה
shmita to remember שמיטה. shmita. But that works fine by the קרקע,
karka, even by the קרקע karka it didn't work fine but okay,
but it actually created problems also with the debt. וראה הלל שנמנעו
העם מלהלוות זה את זה. V'raah Hillel shenimnu ha'am milhalvot zeh et
zeh. And he saw that people were stopping lending. עמד והתקין פרוזבול.
Amad v'hitkin Pruzbul. He established the פרוזבול. Pruzbul. So it works because
the whole annulling of debts in his time and nowadays was, was
דרבנן. d'Rabanan. תוספות Tosafot basically says, no, no, no, in the time
of הלל Hillel it was דאורייתא. d'Oraita. And when הלל Hillel established
the פרוזבול, Pruzbul, it was because he was looking into the future
anticipating that there would be a חורבן הבית Churban HaBayit and it
would be דרבנן d'Rabanan and he made his תקנה takkana for future
time. Very hard to believe that that was the case. Okay, for
whatever reason it was Rabbinic in הלל's Hillel time, we'll say because
there was no יובל, Yovel, certainly it's Rabbinic nowadays, and that's why
the פרוזבול Pruzbul works. So the גמרא Gemara is still not happy,
because how did you make the original תקנה takkana to say that
there would be a Rabbinic annulling of debts? That also is a
question. ומי איכא מידי דמדאורייתא לא משמטה שביעית? U'mi ika midi d'mid'Oraita
lo m'shmita shviit? I don't get it, so let's go back to
the idea that you said that we Rabbinically instituted שמיטה, shmita, right,
before הלל's Hillel פרוזבול. Pruzbul. How could there be a case that
before the rabbis came along there was no שמיטה shmita and the
debts were not annulled, and now the rabbis are telling me that
the debts have to be annulled? You get it? It's not questioning
הלל's Hillel פרוזבול, Pruzbul, it's questioning the establishment of שמיטה, shmita, of
a Rabbinic שמיטה shmita prior to הלל Hillel that annulled the debts.
How did the rabbis establish a שמיטה shmita to annul debts once
it biblically was no longer applicable? How are they getting me, getting
you out of the money that you owe me, right? You understand
the question? Yes? David you give me a look. No? What? I
followed. No, no, no, listen, it's, it's straightforward, okay, I think it
is straightforward, here you have to... I'll draw you a little picture.
Okay. Here you have בית ראשון *Bayit Rishon*. Okay? Where you have
יובל *Yovel*, שמיטת קרקע *Shemittas Karka*, and שמיטת כספים *Shemittas Kesafim*. Okay?
Okay, כספים *Kesafim*. Okay. Then you come to בית שני *Bayit Sheni*
and there's no יובל *Yovel*. Okay. There's only, there's no biblical יובל
*Yovel*. There's only דרבנן *derabbanan* a יובל *Yovel*. Okay. There'll be a
דרבנן *derabbanan* יובל *Yovel*, Rabbinic יובל *Yovel*. Okay. Because there's no יובל
*Yovel*, there's no שמיטת קרקע *Shemittas Karka*. Okay. There's no biblical שמיטת
קרקע *Shemittas Karka*. Because there's no biblical שמיטת קרקע *Shemittas Karka*, there's
no biblical שמיטת כספים *Shemittas Kesafim*. This is all during בית שני
*Bayit Sheni*, right? Okay. But the rabbis are going to reinstitute all
of these things during בית שני *Bayit Sheni*. Okay. And because it's
all Rabbinic, the שמיטת כספים *Shemittas Kesafim*, הלל *Hillel* can come and
say a דרבנן *derabbanan* of פרוזבול pruzbul *Pruzbul*. Okay. פרוזבול *Pruzbul* now
will address the דרבנן *derabbanan* of שמיטת כספים *Shemittas Kesafim*. Okay. That's
what הלל *Hillel*'s doing. Yes? So what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
is, okay, we got now how הלל *Hillel* could make his פרוזבול
*Pruzbul* because it's only attacking a דרבנן *derabbanan* under, you know, sort
of, whatever, compromising a דרבנן *derabbanan* of שמיטת כספים *Shemittas Kesafim*. But
how did they make this דרבנן *derabbanan* of שמיטת כספים *Shemittas Kesafim*?
In the first place, before they made their דרבנן *derabbanan*, money that
was owed had to be paid, right? The biblical annulling stopped. People
had to pay their debts. So how did the rabbis come and
say, "Oh, now we're going to Rabbinically say you don't have to
pay your debt on שמיטה Shemita *Shemitah* because we're going to continue
this idea of שמיטה *Shemitah* Rabbinically"? What allowed them Rabbinically to create
a שמיטה *Shemitah* and to get people out of their debts? You
still have this blank look on your face. That's what הלל *Hillel*
did, right? הלל *Hillel*, הלל *Hillel* stopped the Rabbinic annulling of debts.
But how did the rabbis annul the debts to begin with? The
תורה Torah *Torah*'s שמיטה *Shemitah* stopped, okay, in בית שני *Bayit Sheni*
times. So before the rabbis did anything, people had to pay their
debts during the שמיטה *Shemitah* year. Right? You get it? Before the
rabbis did anything, during בית שני *Bayit Sheni*, if you owed me
money, what happened in the שמיטה *Shemitah* year? What happened in the
שמיטה *Shemitah* year if you owed me money in the בית שני
*Bayit Sheni* time before the rabbis did anything? Nothing. No, you paid.
There was no שמיטה *Shemitah*. You had to pay me. Even on
שמיטה *Shemitah* you paid me, right? Because there was no biblical שמיטה
*Shemitah* and there's no Rabbinic שמיטה *Shemitah*. So the rabbis came and
said, "No, no, no, you don't have to pay anymore. We're instituting
a Rabbinic שמיטה *Shemitah*." What allowed the rabbis to institute a Rabbinic
שמיטה *Shemitah* over the biblical obligation to pay your debts? Okay? So
you got to start. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, "Okay, ומי איכא
מידי דמדאורייתא לא משמטא שביעית *Umi ika midei demide'oraita la meshamta shevi'it*
that biblically שמיטה *Shemitah* would not annul the debt ותקינו רבנן דתשמט
*vetakinu rabbanan detishmat*?" אמר אביי שב ואל תעשה *Amar Abaye shev ve'al
ta'aseh*. Yeah, it's just like we're not actively telling you to violate
a דאורייתא *De'oraita*. We're just passively saying don't pay your debt, don't
collect your debt. Well, don't pay. So yes, that we were able
to say that and institute a Rabbinic שמיטה *Shemitah*. So I don't
get the answer. What does that mean? In other words, like we
tell you not to take the לולב *Lulav* when ראש השנה *Rosh
Hashanah* or סוכות *Sukkot* falls out on שבת *Shabbat*. So we'll tell
you not to pay your debt. Okay. ורבא אמר *VeRava amar*. רבא
*Rava*'s answer is the better one. רבא *Rava* says הפקר בית דין
beis din הפקר *Hefker Beit Din Hefker*. No, rabbis can change. When
it comes to money, the rabbis can manipulate things. Okay? And the
rabbis can release people of their debts. What the בית דין beis
din *Beit Din* says is הפקר *hefker* is ownerless is הפקר *hefker*.
So therefore they were able to institute a Rabbinic שמיטה *Shemitah* and
release people of their debts because they have control over money. Okay,
the rabbis have that power. How do you know that? דאמר רבי
יצחק מניין שהפקר בית דין beis din הפקר *De'amar Rabbi Yitzchak minayin
she'hefker Beit Din hefker*? How do you know that things that the
בית דין beis din *Beit Din* annul become annulled? שנאמר *Shene'emar*, or
not annulled, make ownerless when they sort of, you know, change ownership
of property. וכל אשר לא יבא לשלשת הימים כעצת השרים והזקנים *Vechol
asher lo yavo lishloshet hayamim ke'atzat hasharim vehazekenim*. From בית שני *Bayit
Sheni*, a פסוק *pasuk*. Anybody that does not show up in three
days, כעצת השרים והזקנים *ke'atzat hasharim vehazekenim*, based on the sort of,
you know, advice or whatever, the command, the edict of the officers
and the elders, יחרם כל רכושו *yocharam kol rechusho*, all of his
property will be banned, והוא יבדל מקהל הגולה *vehu yibadel mikel hal'golah*,
and he'll be separated out from the community. So you see that
they have the ability to control ownership of property. רבי אלעזר אמר
מהכא *Rabbi Elazar amar meihacha*. רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* has a different
פסוק *pasuk*, or רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. אלה הנחלות אשר נחלו אלעזר
הכהן ויהושע בן נון *Eileh hanachalot asher nichalu Elazar HaKohen viYehoshua Bin
Nun*. These are the, what's the word נחלות *nachalot*? The lots. The
lot, yeah, but anyway, the portions or whatever. Right. The inheritance. I
know, but it's anyway, the portion, the portion. Anyway, these are the
portions that were bequeathed by אלעזר הכהן *Elazar HaKohen* and יהושע בן
נון *Yehoshua Bin Nun* and the heads of the tribes, etc., when
they were dividing up the land of ישראל *Yisrael*. So why does
it say ראשי אבות *rashei avot*, the heads of the fathers? It
should say the heads of the tribes. וכי מה עניין ראשים אצל
אבות *vechi mah inyan rashim eitzel avot*? What do you mean heads
of the fathers? לומר לך *Lomar lecha*, to tell you, מה אבות
מנחילים את בניהם כל מה שירצו *mah avot manchilim et beneihem kol
mah sheyirtzu*, the same way fathers can bequeath to their children whatever
they want, אף ראשים מנחילים את העם כל מה שירצו *af rashim
manchilim et ha'am kol mah sheyirtzu*, the heads can bequeath to the
people what they want. Now there's a difference between these two דרשות
*drashot*. Because the first דרשה *drasha*, it's only used in the punitive
sense. If you don't show up, your property is put on the
ban, is banned, right? And and you know we're going to take
your property away from you. That's the power of like a court
to like levy fines or to you know you know to seize
your property. Okay, but that's punitive, right? That's the first דרשה *drasha*.
The second דרשה *drasha*, when the same way the heads of the
heads of the nation divvied up the land of Israel, that's not
punitive, that's saying fundamentally they have the right the same way a
father bequeaths to his children they represent the people and they have
the right right to redistribute, you know, the wealth of the nation.
Okay, and that's the difference הפקר בית דין הפקר *hefker beis din
hefker*. Now, Rashi raises an important point. So now what we've said
is שמיטה *shmita* was rabbinic and Hillel's תקנה *takana* and the ways
in which we made a rabbinic שמיטה *shmita* was because we can
control ownership and therefore we can avoid money and therefore we can
void debt. And then Shmuel is able to make his rabbinic institution
which was to which was to what do you call it, which
was to get around that rabbinic law. But Rashi raises a question.
Once we've introduced the idea of הפקר בית דין הפקר *hefker beis
din hefker* that בית דין *beis din* can control money, we have
an answer to our question of how Hillel could get around the
biblical law of שמיטה *shmita*. The law of שמיטה *shmita* could be
biblical, it could be דאורייתא *d'oraisa* the debts are voided and nevertheless
Hillel will allow you to collect your debt after שמיטה *shmita*. How
could he do that? הפקר בית דין הפקר *hefker beis din hefker*.
He just בית דין *beis din* just reinstitutes the debt. The Torah
came along and voided it, fine, the Torah voided your debt and
now we after we won't let you collect let's say during שמיטה
*shmita* or something, but after שמיטה *shmita* we will reinstitute your debt.
Okay, so Rashi says אין הכי נמי *ein hachi nami*. Once the
גמרא *gemara* introduces הפקר בית דין הפקר *hefker beis din hefker*, we
can understand how what פרוזבול *pruzbul* does how Hillel does work even
against the Torah's you know what do you call it the Torah's
שמיטה *shmita*. תוספות Tosfos *tosafos* disagree. תוספות Tosfos *tosafos* say if you
look in ל"ו עמוד א' *lamed vav amud aleph* הכי קאמר דאי
דמדאורייתא משמטי שביעית *hachi ka amar d'i d'mide'oraisa mshamtat shvi'is* תוספות Tosfos
*tosafos* ואתקין הלל דלא משמטי *v'atkin hillel d'lo mshamtat* תוספות Tosfos *tosafos*
says השתא לא בעי רבא לישנויי האי קושיא דהפקר בית דין היה
הפקר *hashta lo ba'i rava lishnuyei hai kushya d'hefker beis din haya
hefker*. Why didn't Rava give the answer here's how Hillel could do
could go against the Torah's שמיטה *shmita* because of הפקר בית דין
הפקר *hefker beis din hefker*? Why didn't he give that answer? דמשני
ברייתא הכי משום דקשיא ליה דלא היה לו להלל לעקור שביעית שהיא
דאורייתא *d'mshani barsa hachi mishum d'kashya leh d'lo haya lo l'hillel la'akor
shvi'is she-hi d'oraisa*. Meaning, what תוספות Tosfos *tosafos* is saying is the
problem wasn't what mechanism is available to Hillel. Hillel maybe has a
mechanism to do פרוזבול *pruzbul* to get around the Torah's law of
שמיטה *shmita*. The question is how could you do such a thing?
How could you blatantly go against and you know and you know
and undermine a Torah institution? Sure you have the mechanism, but why
are you going what would let you use that mechanism? Right, in
such a in such a blatant way. Now, could say well I'm
trying to ultimately preserve the Torah because I'm trying to get people
to lend money and not violate, that all might be very nice
but you know you can't do it in such a blatant way
or you can't do it in a way that really challenges in
that profound way a biblical institution. So I want to say that
there's an interesting parallel to what we said before about about הפקעת
קידושין *hafk'as kiddushin*. When we learned הפקעת קידושין *hafk'as kiddushin* I mentioned
to you the position of the רשב"א *Rashba* that says yes, the
rabbis do have the power to retroactively annul a marriage, but they
will never do it retroactively because you know that's such a blatant
like you know show of power that we the rabbis are going
to go ahead and and you know and something that for the
last 20 years they've been happily married and it's been recognized as
a biblical marriage and we want to say it never existed. That
like is a blatant show of like you know of rabbinic power
against a biblical institution. So we need to what I call this
the fig leaf approach, we need to hide behind something that it
doesn't look that it's not an obvious challenge to the biblical institution
of marriage. So we're only going to say הפקעת קידושין *hafk'as kiddushin*
when there's a גט *get*. The גט *get* might be פסול *pasul*,
okay, but if there is a גט *get* even if it's a
פסול *pasul* one, it doesn't look like we are voiding the קידושין
*kiddushin*, it looks like she's divorced by the גט *get*. So the
same thing you could say is true here. Remember I said to
you that the logic of פרוזבול *pruzbul* was that it was giving
over the debt to בית דין *beis din*, okay, but if that's
true, I mean you know why do you need that logic at
all? And the point is you know I mean or if that
logic works why do you need Hillel's תקנה *takana*? And the answer
could be that maybe that doesn't really work, or it really doesn't
work to give over your debt to בית דין *beis din*. You're
not really giving them over to בית דין *beis din*. But it
serves as the fig leaf because we can't go ahead and just
blatantly say oh so the Torah's law you know the Torah's thing
doesn't apply because we did something Hillel asked us to do. Right?
There has to be a logic in which it doesn't it's not
coming across as a straight override of the Torah institution. So there's
two points: number one is תוספות *tosafos* saying is saying like you
know why would we ever like how could we have the חוצפה
*chutzpah* to go ahead and to undermine a Torah institution? And the
answer might be okay okay by Hillel's day it was only rabbinic,
it wasn't really a Torah one. Now how do we have the
mechanism? How do we How could we, the authority or right or
you know or would we do such thing so blatant? You might
have the mechanism to do it but how could you do it?
And the and the answer was it was only rabbinic. Okay, but
רש"י says it could even be biblical but the other question that
I'm pointing out is how would we we couldn't sort of you
know do it in a way that was blatant even when we
were doing it and therefore it was important to use this the
the mechanism that that even if it was didn't really work looked
like it worked and that was the mechanism of giving it over
giving the debt over to the בית דין and that's the end
of this תוספות if you just read the next line of תוספות
he says ואף על גב דדרשינן בספרי ואשר יהיה לך את אחיך
תשמט ידך ולא שלך ביד בית דין מכאן אמרו המלווה את חבירו
על המשכון והמוסר שטרותיו לבית דין אין משמטין ve'af al gav de'darshinan
be'Sifrei va'asher yihiyeh lecha et achicha tashmet yadecha velo shelach beyad beis
din mikan amru hamalveh et chaveiro al hamashkon vehamoseir shetarotav le'beis din
ein meshamtin there's only when the debt is to you but if
you hand it over to בית דין it's not annulled. תוספות says
מכל מקום לא היה לו לעשות תקנה וללמד לעשות כך שבביטול שמיטת
כספים mikol makom lo hayah lo la'asot takanah u'lelamed la'asot kach shebe'vittul
shemitas kesafim and then he says and anyway whatever so that's the
second answer I shouldnt right the next answer is it gets a
little confusing but the next answer תוספות says is first is that
that's really just a אסמכתא asmakhta that really it doesn't work to
hand I mean it's two answers but the second answer is it
doesn't work to hand it over to בית דין but we need
it to look like it worked. Okay so again in this context
of the idea of תיקון עולם tikkun olam the upshot is because
this is often lost on people that you know see this פרוזבול
as this whole big model of rabbinic power you know like where
there's a rabbinic will there's a halakhic way which it might be
but it's important to understand some of the some of the qualities
of it because of how we frame the issues. We don't frame
it like oh this תורה Torah law doesn't work it's too heavy
on the people let's find a workaround. It was framed as this
תורה Torah law is coming at the cost of another of תורה
מצוה Torah mitzvah it's one מצוה mitzvah against another מצוה mitzvah because
of שמיטה people are transgressing so we have to find a way
to solve that balance. It's not framed in terms of the cost
to the people although that might be what motivates you which side
of the scale you tip it about. The other issue is is
that we're not just going to go ahead and blatantly override a
תורה law. According to תוספות the whole question in the גמרא is
we know you have the mechanism but that doesn't mean that you
have the you should have the will or the ability or the
propriety of doing such a thing it might only be a rabbinic
law okay and the other thing is even when we are overriding
it or if we are we're going to not again do it
blatantly but we're going to do it through a mechanism of handing
it over to בית דין which may or may not work but
at least it looks like it works and that's also part part
of this whole process. Is it kind of is it kind of
a legal